const quizData = [
{
    question: 'With reference to Indian freedom struggle, consider the following events:

Mutiny in Royal Indian Navy
Quit India Movement launched
Second Round Table Conference
What is the correct chronological sequence of the above events?',

a: '1-2-3',

b: '2-1-3',

c: '3-2-1',

d: '3-1-2',

correct: 'c'
},

{
question: 'The object of the Butler Committee of 1927 was to?',

a: 'Define the jurisdiction of the Central and Provincial Governments.',

b: Define the powers of the Secretary of State for India.',

c: 'Impose censorship on national press.',

d: 'Improve the relationship between the Government of India and the Indian States.',

correct: 'd'
},

{

 question: 'Consider the following pairs:Radhakanta Deb — First President of the British Indian Association
Gazulu Lakshminarasu Chetty —Founder of the Madras Mahajana Sabha
Surendranath Banerjee — Founder of the Indian Association
Which of the above pairs is/are correctly matched?',
 a: '1 only',
 b: '1 and 3 only',
 c: '2 and 3 only',
 d: '1, 2 and 3',
 correct: 'b'
},


{

 question: 'Who among the following was/were associated with the introduction of Ryotwari Settlement in India during the British rule? Lord Cornwallis
Alexander Read
Thomas Munro
Select the correct answer using the code given below:',
 a: '1 only',
 b: '1 and 3 only',
 c: '2 and 3 only',
 d: 'v',
 correct: 'c'
},

{

 question: 'The staple commodities of export by the English East India Company from Bengal in the middle of the 18th century were',
 a: 'Raw cotton, oil-seeds, and opium',
 b: 'Sugar, salt, zinc, and lead',
 c: 'Copper, silver, gold, spices, and tea',
 d: 'Cotton, silk, saltpeter, and opium',
 correct: 'd'
},

{

 question: 'Which one of the following is a very significant aspect of the Champaran Satyagraha?',
 a: 'Active all-India participation of lawyers, students and women in the National Movement',
 b: 'Active involvement of Dalit and Tribal communities of India in the National Movement',
 c: 'Joining of peasant unrest to India's National Movement',
 d: 'Drastic decrease in the cultivation of plantation crops and commercial crops',
 correct: 'c'
},

 Q2- Which one of the following is a very significant aspect of the Champaran Satyagraha?

(a) Active all-India participation of lawyers, students and women in the National Movement
(b) Active involvement of Dalit and Tribal communities of India in the National Movement
(c) Joining of peasant unrest to India's National Movement
(d) Drastic decrease in the cultivation of plantation crops and commercial crops

Answer.c
},

{

 question: 'Who among the following were the founders of the "Hind Mazdoor Sabha" established in 1948 ?',
 a: 'B. Krishna Pillai, E.M.S. Namboodiripad and K.C. George',
 b: 'Jayaprakash Narayan, Deen Day al Upadhyay and M.N. Roy',
 c: 'C.P. Ramaswamy Iyer, K. Kamaraj and Veeresalingam Pantulu',
 d: 'Ashok Mehta, T.S. Ramanujam and G.G. Mehta',
 correct: 'd'
},

{

 question: 'Which one of the following statements does not apply to the system of Subsidiary Alliance introduced by Lord Wellesley?',
 a: 'To maintain a large standing army at other's expense',
 b: 'To keep India safe from Napoleonic danger',
 c: 'To secure a fixed income for the Company',
 d: 'To establish British paramountcy over the Indian States',
 correct: 'b'
},
]



{

 question: 'He wrote biographies of Mazzini, Garibaldi, Shivaji and Shrikrishna; stayed in America for some time; and was also elected to the Central Assembly. He was',
 a: 'Aurobindo Ghosh',
 b: 'Bipin Chandra Pal',
 c: 'Lala Lajpat Rai',
 d: 'Motilal Nehru',
 correct: 'c'
},




const quizDta = [

    {

 question: '',
 a: '',
 b: '',
 c: '',
 d: '',
 correct: ''
},

Q6- After the Santhal Uprising subsided, what was/were the measure/measures taken by the colonial government?

The territories called `Santhal Paraganas' were created.
2. It became illegal for a Santhal to transfer land to a non-Santhal.
Select the correct answer using the code given below:
(a) 1 only
(b) 2 only
(c) Both 1 and 2
(d) Neither 1 nor 2
Answer.c

{

 question: '',
 a: '',
 b: '',
 c: '',
 d: '',
 correct: ''
},

Q7- Economically, one of the results of the British rule in India in the 19th century was the

(a) increase in the export of Indian handicrafts
(b) growth in the number of Indian owned factories
(c) commercialization of Indian agriculture
(d) rapid increase in the urban population

Answer.c

{

 question: '',
 a: '',
 b: '',
 c: '',
 d: '',
 correct: ''
},

Q8- Which of the following led to the introduction of English Education in India ?

Charter Act of 1813
2. General Committee of Public Instruction, 1823
3. Orientalist and Anglicist Controversy
Select the correct answer using the code given below

(a) 1 and 2 only
(b) 2 only
(c) 1 and 3 only
(d) 1, 2 and 3

Answer.a

{

 question: '',
 a: '',
 b: '',
 c: '',
 d: '',
 correct: ''
},

Q9- In 1920, which of the following changed its name to “Swarajya Sabha”?

(a) All India Home Rule League
(b) Hindu Mahasabha
(c) South Indian Liberal Federation
(d) The Servants of India Society

Answer.a

{

 question: '',
 a: '',
 b: '',
 c: '',
 d: '',
 correct: ''
},

Q10- Which among the following events happened earliest ?

(a) Swami Dayanand established AryaSamaj.
(b) Dinabandhu Mitra wrote Neeldarpan.
(c) Bankim Chandra Chattopadhyay wrote Anandmath.
(d) Satyendranath Tagore became the first Indian to succeed in the Indian Civil Services Examination.

Answer.b

{

 question: '',
 a: '',
 b: '',
 c: '',
 d: '',
 correct: ''
},

 Q11- With reference to educational institutes during colonial rule in India, consider the following pairs :

            Institution                             Founder

1. Sanskrit College at Benaras -      William Jones
2. Calcutta Madarsa    -                Warren Hastings
3. Fort William College     -             Arthur Wellesley

Which of the pairs given above is/are correct ?

(a) 1 and 2
(b) 2 only
(c) 1 and 3
(d) 3 only

Answer.b

{

 question: '',
 a: '',
 b: '',
 c: '',
 d: '',
 correct: ''
},

Q12- Regarding Wood's Dispatch, which of the following statements are true ?

Grants-in-Aid system was introduced.
2. Establishment of universities was recommended.
3. English as a medium of instruction at all levels of education was recommended.
Select the correct answer using the code given below :
(a) 1 and 2 only
(b) 2 and 3 only
(c) 1 and 3 only
(d) 1, 2 and 3
Answer. A

{

 question: '',
 a: '',
 b: '',
 c: '',
 d: '',
 correct: ''
},

Q1- With reference to land reforms in independent India, which one of the following statements is correct?

(a) The ceiling "laws were aimed at family holdings and not individual holdings.

(b) The major aim of land reforms was to provide agricultural land to all the landless.

(c) It resulted in the cultivation of cash crops as a predominant form of cultivation.

(d) Land reforms permitted no exemptions to the ceiling limits.

Answer: b

{

 question: '',
 a: '',
 b: '',
 c: '',
 d: '',
 correct: ''
},

Q2- Consider the following statements about 'the Charter Act of 1813':

It ended the trade monopoly of the East India Company in India except for trade in tea and trade with China.
It asserted the sovereignty of the British Crown over the Indian territories held by the Company.
The revenues of India were now controlled by the British Parliament.
Which of the statements given above are correct?

(a) 1 and 2 only

(b) 2 and 3 only

(c) 1 and 3 only

(d) 1, 2 and 3

Answer: a

]

Q3- With reference to the Swadeshi Movement, consider the following statements:

It contributed to the revival of the indigenous artisan crafts and industries.
The National Council of Education was established as a part of Swadeshi Movement.
Which of the statements given above is/are correct?

(a) 1 only

(b) 2 only

(c) Both 1 and 2

(d) Neither 1 nor 2

Answer: c

Q4- Consider the following pairs:

Movement/Organization

Leader

1. All India Anti-Untouchability League

Mahatma Gandhi

2. All India Kisan Sabha

Swami Sahajanand Saraswati

3. Self-Respect Movement

E. V. Ramaswami Naicker

Which of the pairs given above is/are correctly matched?

(a) 1 only

(b) 1 and 2 only

(c) 2 and 3 only

(d) 1, 2 and 3

Answer: d

Q5- With reference to the British colonial rule in India, consider the following statements:

Mahatma Gandhi was instrumental in the abolition of the system of 'indentured labour'.
In Lord Chelmsford's 'War Conference', Mahatma Gandhi did not support the resolution on recruiting Indians for World War.
Consequent upon the breaking of Salt Law by Indian people, the Indian National Congress was declared illegal by the colonial rulers.
Which of the statements given above are correct?

(a) 1 and 2 only

(b) 1 and 3 only

(c) 2 and 3 only

(d) 1, 2 and 3

Answer: b

Q6- With reference to Indian National Movement, consider the following pairs:

Person

Position held

1. Sir Tej Bahadur Sapru

President, All India Liberal Federation

2. K. C. Neogy

Member, The Constituent Assembly

3. P. C. Joshi

General Secretary, Communist Party of India

Which of the pairs given above is/are correctly matched?

(a) 1 only

(b) 1 and 2 only

(c) 3 only

(d) 1, 2 and 3

Answer: d

--------------
--------------

Q1- With reference to Indian history, which of the following is/are the essential elements of the feudal system?

1.A very strong centralized political authority and a very weak provincial or local political authority
2. The emergence of administrative structure based on control and possession of the land
3. Creation of the lord-vassal relationship between the feudal lord and his overlord

Select the correct answer using the code given below.

(a) 1 and 2 only
(b) 2 and 3 only
(c)  3 only  
(d) 1, 2 and 3

Answer. a

 Q2- Which one of the following movements has contributed to a split in the Indian National Congress resulting in the emergence of 'moderates' and 'extremists'?

(a) Swadeshi Movement
(b) Quit India Movement
(c) Non-Cooperation Movement
(d) Civil Disobedience Movement

Answer. A

 Q3- With reference to Rowlatt Satyagraha, which of the following statements is/ are correct?

The Rowlatt Act was based on the recommendations of the 'Sedition Committee'.
2. In Rowlatt Satyagraha, Gandhiji tried to utilize the Home Rule League.
3. Demonstrations against the arrival of Simon Commission coincided with Rowlatt Satyagraha.
Select the correct answer using the code given below.

(a) 1 only
(b) 1 and 2 only
(c) 2 and 3 only
(d) 1, 2 and 3

Answer. B

 Q4- Who of the following was/were economic critic/ critics of colonialism in India?

Dadabhai Naoroji
2. G. Subramania Iyer
3. R. C. Dutt
Select the correct answer using the code given below.

(a) 1 only     
(b) 1 and 2 only
(c) 2 and 3 only
(d) 1, 2 and 3

Answer. D

 Q5- With reference to Congress Socialist Party, consider the following statements:

It advocated the boycott of British goods and evasion of taxes.
2. It wanted to establish the dictatorship of proletariat.
3. It advocated separate electorate for minorities and oppressed classes.
Which of the statements given above is / are correct?

(a) 1 and 2 only
(b) 3 only     
(c) 1, 2 and 3
(d) None

Answer. D

 Q6- The Government of India Act of 1919 clearly defined

(a) the separation of power between the judiciary and the legislature
(b) the jurisdiction of the central and provincial governments
(c) the powers of the Secretary of State for India and the Viceroy
(d) None of the above

Answer. B

 Q7- Who of the following organized a march on the Tanjore coast to break the Salt Law in April 1930?

(a) V. O. Chidambaram Pillai
(b) C. Rajagopalachari
(c) K. Kamaraj
(d) Annie Besant

Answer. B

 Q8- Consider the following statements

1.The first woman President of the Indian National Congress was Sarojini Naidu.
2. The first Muslim President of the Indian National Congress was Badruddin Tyabji.

Which of the statements given above is / are correct?

(a) 1 only
(b) 2 only
(c) Both 1 and 2
(d) Neither 1 nor 2

Answer. b

-----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------

Question for IAS Exam 2020 (Essay Topics)
NITI Aayog is better than its predecessor. Critically Analyse.
India presents a good example of Cooperative Federalism. Discuss.
India will be able to reap the benefits of Demographic dividend. Critically Analyse.
Agrarian reforms are essential for the growth of Indian Economy. Discuss.
Health infrastructure in India requires community participation. Discuss.
Technology and Artificial Intelligence can replace human intervention. Critically Analyse.
Covid-19 had an impact on the Social Fabric of Indian Society. Discuss.
Recent diplomatic discussions with our neighbours have proved that India is an emerging power?
What does the Non-Permanent Seat of UNSC mean for India in changing scenario?
India is ready to take up greater responsibilities in changing world order.
Questions for IAS Exam 2020 (Mains)
COVID-19 pandemic has opened the fractures of the Indian Health Infrastructure?
Corona-virus pandemic has increased the rural-urban divide. Discuss.
What is Virtual Private Network(VPN) and how it is different from LAN?
India should make more stringent drug trial regulations so that false claims can be minimised. Discuss
Indian Medical Service is the demand of the present time. Discuss
It is a high time to notify the Health in the Union List. Discuss
Our police should be better equipped to control COVID-19 like situations? Discuss.
In the times of pandemic like Corona, what are the most expected quality required from a Civil Servant?
The change in work culture post lockdown can be a boon to control pollution? Discuss.
It is a high time to create All India Health Services? Critically examine.
How technology can change Health Services in India?
Discuss the important changes in India's Foreign Policy in the recent past.
See here: UPSC Essay Topics

Questions for UPSC Prelims exam
Questions for UPSC 2021 (Prelims) can include the following. The list will be updated with new questions.

What is the 'Verified' initiative?
What is Navigating the new normal?
What is 'Ek Bharat Shreshtha Bharat' initiative?
What is the minimum number of Solar and Lunar eclipse takes place in a year?
What is the rainfall pattern in North-East India?
What was the origin point of Cyclone Nisarga?
How the cyclones are named?
What was the origin point of Cyclone Amphan?
What is LAC means?
What is the size of the coronavirus?
When does the LAC was marked and agreed?
Where is Dholavira located?
In which state the Lipu Lake exist?
What is mentioned in Article 370 H
What is the impact of the REPO RATE increase on Economy?
Right to vote is a fundamental right. True or False.
Financial Emergency is defined in our constitution. True or false.
Which river takes a hairpin turn in the east?
The Union, State and concurrent list are associated with which article of the Constitution of India.
“Health” is a Union subject. True or False.
Who has the residuary powers regarding the matters enumerated in the concurrent list?
What is cryptocurrency?
What is BlockChain technology
The amendment in the Citizenship provisions mentioned in the Constitution of India requires a special majority. True or False.
When did Mahatma Gandhi go for the Third Round Table conference?
What is Rights Issue?
Where did the Indian Science Congress was organised.